<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- Created from PDF via Acrobat SaveAsXML -->
<!-- Mapping Table version: 28-February-2003 -->
<TaggedPDF-doc>
<?xpacket begin='﻿' id='W5M0MpCehiHzreSzNTczkc9d'?>
<?xpacket begin="﻿" id="W5M0MpCehiHzreSzNTczkc9d"?>
<x:xmpmeta xmlns:x="adobe:ns:meta/" x:xmptk="Adobe XMP Core 9.1-c001 79.675d0f7, 2023/06/11-19:21:16        ">
   <rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
      <rdf:Description rdf:about=""
            xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
            xmlns:xmp="http://ns.adobe.com/xap/1.0/"
            xmlns:pdf="http://ns.adobe.com/pdf/1.3/"
            xmlns:xmpMM="http://ns.adobe.com/xap/1.0/mm/">
         <dc:format>xml</dc:format>
         <dc:title>
            <rdf:Alt>
               <rdf:li xml:lang="x-default">Microsoft Word - DDEX14 Dues for the Dead.docx</rdf:li>
            </rdf:Alt>
         </dc:title>
         <dc:creator>
            <rdf:Seq>
               <rdf:li>tulachc</rdf:li>
            </rdf:Seq>
         </dc:creator>
         <xmp:CreateDate>2014-08-22T02:00:22-07:00</xmp:CreateDate>
         <xmp:CreatorTool>PScript5.dll Version 5.2.2</xmp:CreatorTool>
         <xmp:ModifyDate>2014-08-22T02:00:22-07:00</xmp:ModifyDate>
         <pdf:Producer>Acrobat Distiller 10.0.0 (Windows)</pdf:Producer>
         <xmpMM:DocumentID>uuid:3a5d32c4-623a-4819-a86f-48e3d43da6f7</xmpMM:DocumentID>
         <xmpMM:InstanceID>uuid:04dfaf94-e6be-4884-9d6c-527bb3f1c70e</xmpMM:InstanceID>
      </rdf:Description>
   </rdf:RDF>
</x:xmpmeta>
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                           
<?xpacket end="w"?>
<?xpacket end='r'?>
<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_0.jpg"/>
F p R For years, the M peaceful eterna Radiance. An ad D Most Solemn O al rest.  Now, th dventure for 1s Dues Order of the Sile hat rest has bee st-4th level cha for ent Shroud has en disturbed by aracters. r the s tended the de y a necromance e De ead at Valinghe er seeking out a ead en graveyard, p a key to re-activ providing them vate the Pool o a of </Figure>

<Part>
<Sect>
<H4>Adventure Code: DDEXX1‐4 </H4>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H5>CCredits </H5>
</Sect>

<P>AAdventure Designn: Steve Winter DDevelopment andd Editing: Claire HHoffman, Chris TTulach, Travis Wooodall DD&amp;D Organized PPlay: Chris Tulach DD&amp;D R&amp;D Playerr Experience: Greeg Bilsland DD&amp;D Adventurerss League Wizardss Team: Greg Bilsland, Chris Linddsay, Shelly Mazzzanoble, Chris Tulach DD&amp;D Adventurerss League Administrators: Robert Adducci, Bill Bennham, Travis Wooodall, Claire Hofffman, Greg Marrks, Alan Patrick </P>

<Sect><Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_1.jpg"/>
</Figure>

<P>DDebut: August 288, 2014 RRelease: October 1, 2014 </P>
</Sect>

<P>DDUNGEONS &amp; DRRAGONS, D&amp;D, WWizards of the Coast, Forgotten Reaalms, the dragon ampersand, Playeer’s Handbook, Moonster Manual, Duungeon MMaster’s Guide, D&amp;&amp;D Adventurers Leeague, D&amp;D Encoounters, D&amp;D Expeditions, D&amp;D Eppics, all other Wizaards of the Coast product names, aand thheir respective loggos are trademarkks of Wizards of thhe Coast in the USSA and other counntries. All characteers and their distinctive likenesses are pproperty of Wizardds of the Coast. Thhis material is prootected under the ccopyright laws of the United Statess of America. Any reproduction or uunauthorized use of the material or artwork containedd herein is prohibbited without the eexpress written peermission of Wizards of the Coast. </P>

<P>©©2014 Wizards off the Coast LLC, PPO Box 707, Rentoon, WA 98057-0707, USA. Manufacttured by Hasbro SSA, Rue Emile-Boééchat 31, 2800 DDelémont, CH. Represented by Hassbro Europe, 4 Thee Square, Stockleyy Park, Uxbridge, MMiddlesex, UB11 1ET, UK. </P>

<P>Not for rresale. Permission granted to print oor photocopy this document for perrsonal use only. </P>
</Sect>
</Part>

<Part>
<H2>Introduction </H2>

<P>Welcome to Dues for the Dead, a D&amp;D ExpeditionsTM adventure, part of the official D&amp;D Adventurers LeagueTM organized play system and the Tyranny of DragonsTM storyline season.  </P>

<P>This adventure is designed for three to seven 1st4th level characters, and is optimized for five 2nd level characters. Characters outside this level range cannot participate in this adventure. Players with ineligble characters can create a new 1st-level character or use a pregenerated character. </P>

<P>The adventure takes place in Phlan, a large city on the shore of the Moonsea, in the Forgotten Realms. More specifically, it takes place almost entirely in and beneath the city's cemetery, Valhingen Graveyard. </P>
</Part>

<Part>
<H2>The D&amp;D Adventurers League </H2>

<P>This adventure is official for D&amp;D Adventurers League play. The D&amp;D Adventurers League is the official organized play system for DUNGEONS &amp; DRAGONS®. Players can create characters and participate in any adventure allowed as a part of the D&amp;D Adventurers League. As they adventure, players track their characters’ experience, treasure, and other rewards, and can take those characters through other adventures that will continue their story. </P>

<P>D&amp;D Adventurers League play is broken up into storyline seasons. When players create characters, they attach those characters to a storyline season, which determines what rules they’re allowed to use to create and advance their characters. Players can continue to play their characters after the storyline season has finished, possibly participating in a second or third storyline with those same characters. A character’s level is the only limitation for adventure play. A player cannot use a character of a level higher or lower than the level range of a D&amp;D Adventurers League adventure. </P>

<P>If you’re running this adventure as a part of a store event or at certain conventions, you’ll need a DCI number. This number is your official Wizards of the Coast organized play identifier. If you don’t have a number, you can obtain one at a store event. Check with your organizer for details. </P>

<P>For more information on playing, running games as a Dungeon Master, and organizing games for the D&amp;D Adventurers League, please visit the D&amp;D Adventurers League home. </P>
</Part>

<Part>
<H2>Preparing the Adventure </H2>

<P>Before you show up to Dungeon Master this adventure for a group of players, you should do the following to prepare. </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Make sure to have a copy of the most current version of the D&amp;D basic rules or the Player’sHandbookTM. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Read through the adventure, taking notes of anything you’d like to highlight or remind yourself while running the adventure, such as a way you’d like to portray an NPC or a tactic you’d like to use in a combat. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Get familiar with the monster statistics in the Appendix. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Gather together any resources you’d like to use to aid you in Dungeon Mastering, such as notecards, a DM screen, miniatures, battlemaps, etc. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>If you know the composition of the group beforehand, you can make adjustments as noted throughout the adventure.  </LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</Part>

<Part>
<Sect>
<H2>Before Play at the Table </H2>

<P>Ask the players to provide you with relevant character information. This includes: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Character name and level </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Character race and class </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Passive Wisdom (Perception)—the most common passive ability check </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Anything notable as specified by the adventure (such as backgrounds, traits, flaws, and so on) </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Players that have characters outside the adventure’s level range cannot participate in the adventure with those characters. Players with ineligible characters can make a new 1st-level character or use a pregenerated character. Players can play an adventure they previously played or ran as a Dungeon Master, but not with the same character (if applicable). </P>

<P>Ensure that each player has an official adventure logsheet for his or her character (if not, get one from the organizer). The player will fill out the adventure name, session number, date, and your name and DCI number. In addition, the player also fills in the starting values for XP, gold, downtime, renown, and number of permanent magic items. He or she will fill in the other values and </P>

<P>Dues for the Dead </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>write notes at the conclusion of the session. Each player is responsible for maintaining an accurate logsheet.  </P>

<P>If you have time, you can do a quick scan of a player’s character sheet to ensure that nothing looks out of order. If you see magic items of very high rarities or strange arrays of ability scores, you can ask players to provide documentation for the irregularities. If they cannot, feel free to restrict item use or ask them to use a standard ability score array. Point players to the D&amp;D Adventurers League Player’s Guide for reference. </P>

<P>If players wish to spend downtime days and it’s the beginning of an adventure or episode, they can declare their activity and spend the days now, or they can do so at the end of the adventure or episode.  </P>

<P>Players should select their characters’ spells and other daily options prior to the start of the adventure, unless the adventure specifies otherwise. Feel free to reread the adventure description to help give players hints about what they might face. </P>
</Sect>
</Part>

<Part>
<H2>Adjusting the Adventure </H2>

<P>Throughout this adventure, you may see sidebars to help you make adjustments to this adventure for smaller/larger groups and characters, of higher/lower levels that the optimized group size. Most of the time, this is used for combat encounters.  </P>

<P>You may adjust the adventure beyond the guidelines given in the adventure, or for other reasons. For example, if you’re playing with a group of inexperienced players, you might want to make the adventure a little easier; for very experienced players, you might want to make it a little harder. Therefore, five categories of party strength have been created for you to use as a guide. Use these as a guide, and feel free to use a different adjustment during the adventure if the recommended party strength feels off for the group. </P>

<P>This adventure is optimized for a party of five 2ndlevel characters. To figure out whether you need to adjust the adventure, do the following: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Add up the total levels of all the characters </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Divide the total by the number of characters </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Round fractions of .5 or greater up; round frations of less than .5 down </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>You’ve now determined the average party level (APL) for the adventure. To figure out the party strength for the adventure, consult the following table. </P>

<Sect>
<H5>Determining Party Strength </H5>

<Sect>
<H6>Party Composition   Party Strength </H6>

<P>3-4 characters, APL less than Very weak 3-4 characters, APL equivalent Weak 3-4 characters, APL greater than Average 5 characters, APL less than Weak 5 characters, APL equivalent Average 5 characters, APL greater than Strong 6-7 characters, APL less than Average 6-7 characters, APL equivalent Strong 6-7 characters, APL greater than Very strong </P>

<P>Average party strength indicates no recommended adjustments to the adventure. Each sidebar may or may not offer suggestions for certain party strengths. If a particular recommendation is not offered for your group, you don’t have to make adjustments.  </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Part>

<Part>
<Sect>
<H2>Dungeon Mastering the Adventure </H2>

<P>As the DM of the session, you have the most important role in facilitating the enjoyment of the game for the players. You help guide the narrative and bring the words on these pages to life. The outcome of a fun game session often creates stories that live well beyond the play at the table. Always follow this golden rule when you DM for a group: </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H5>Make decisions and adjudications that enhance the fun of the adventure when possible. </H5>

<P>To reinforce this golden rule, keep in mind the following: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>You are empowered to make adjustments to the adventure and make decisions about how the group interacts with the world of this adventure. This is especially important and applicable outside of combat, but feel free to adjust the adventure for groups that are having too easy or too hard of a time. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Don’t make the adventure too easy or too difficult for a group. Never being challenged makes for a boring game, and being overwhelmed makes for a frustrating game. Gauge the experience of the players (not the characters) with the game, try to feel out (or ask) what they like in a game, and attempt to give each of them the experience they’re after when they play D&amp;D. Give everyone a chance to shine. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Dues for the Dead </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<L>
<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Be mindful of pacing, and keep the game session moving along appropriately. Watch for stalling, since play loses momentum when this happens. At the same time, make sure that the players don’t finish too early; provide them with a full play experience. Try to be aware of running long or short. Adjust the pacing accordingly. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Read-aloud text is just a suggestion; feel free to modify the text as you see fit, especially when dialogue is present. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Give the players appropriate hints so they can make informed choices about how to proceed. Players should be given clues and hints when appropriate so they can tackle puzzles, combat, and interactions without getting frustrated over lack of information. This helps to encourage immersion in the adventure and gives players “little victories” for figuring out good choices from clues. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>In short, being the DM isn’t about following the adventure’s text word-for-word; it’s about facilitating a fun, challenging game environment for the players. The Dungeon Master’s Guide TM has more information on the art of running a D&amp;D game. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Downtime and Lifestyle </H3>

<P>At the beginning of each play session, players must declare whether or not they are spending any days of downtime. The player records the downtime spent on the adventure logsheet. The following options are available to players during downtime (see the D&amp;D basic rules or the D&amp;D Adventurers League Player’s Guide for more information): </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Catching up </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Crafting (exception: multiple characters cannot commit to crafting a single item) </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Practicing a profession </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Recuperating </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Spellcasting services (end of the adventure only) </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Training </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Other downtime options might be available during adventures or unlocked through play, including faction-specific activities. </P>

<P>In addition, whenever a character spends downtime days, that character also spends the requisite expense for his or her lifestyle. Costs are per day, so a character that spends ten days of downtime also spends ten days of expenses maintaining his or her lifestyle. Some downtime activities help with lifestyle expenses or add lifestyle expenses. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Spellcasting Services </H3>

<P>Any settlement the size of a town or larger can provide some spellcasting services. Characters need to be able to travel to the settlement to obtain these services. Alternatively, if the party finishes an adventure, they can be assumed to return to the settlement closest to the adventure location. </P>

<P>Spell services generally available include healing and recovery spells, as well as information-gathering spells. Other spell services might be available as specified in the adventure. The number of spells available to be cast as a service is limited to a maximum of three per day </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TH>total, unless otherwise noted.  </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Spellcasting Services </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Spell </TH>

<TD>Cost </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Cure wounds (1st level) </TH>

<TD>10 gp </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Identify </TH>

<TD>20 gp </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Lesser restoration </TH>

<TD>40 gp </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Prayer of healing (2nd level) </TH>

<TD>40 gp </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Remove curse </TH>

<TD>90 gp </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Speak with dead </TH>

<TD>90 gp </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Divination </TH>

<TD>210 gp </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Greater restoration </TH>

<TD>450 gp </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Raise dead </TH>

<TD>1,250 gp </TD>
</TR>
</Table>

<Sect>
<H5>Acolyte Background </H5>

<P>A character possessing the acolyte background requesting </P>

<P>spellcasting services at a temple of his or her faith may request </P>

<P>one spell per day from the Spellcasting Services table for free. </P>

<P>The only cost paid for the spell is the base price for the </P>

<P>consumed material component, if any. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Character Disease, Death, and Recovery </H3>

<P>Sometimes bad things happen, and characters get poisoned, diseased, or die. Since you might not have the same characters return from session to session, here are the rules when bad things happen to characters. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H4>Disease, Poison, and Other Debilitating Effects </H4>

<P>A character still affected by diseases, poisons, and other similar effects at the conclusion of an adventure can spend downtime days recuperating until such time as he or she resolves the effect to its conclusion (see the recuperating activity in the D&amp;D basic rules). If a </P>

<P>Dues for the Dead </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>character doesn’t resolve the effect between sessions, that character begins the next session still affected by the debilitating effect. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Death </H4>

<P>A character who dies during the course of the adventure has a few options at the end of the session (or whenever arriving back in civilization) if no one in the adventuring party has immediate access to a raise dead or revivify spell, or similar magic. A character subject to a raise dead spell is affected negatively until all long rests have been completed during an adventure. Alternatively, each downtime day spent after raise dead reduces the penalty to attack rolls, saving throws, and ability checks by 1, in addition to any other benefits the downtime activity might provide. </P>

<P>Create a New 1st-Level Character. If the dead character is unwilling or unable to exercise any of the other options, the player creates a new character. The new character does not have any items or rewards possessed by the dead character. </P>

<P>Dead Character Pays for Raise Dead. If the character’s body is recoverable (it’s not missing any vital organs and is mostly whole) and the player would like the character to be returned to life, the party can take the body back to civilization and use the dead character’s funds to pay for a raise dead spell. A raise dead spell cast in this manner costs the character 1,250 gp. </P>

<P>Character’s Party Pays for Raise Dead. As above, except that some or all of the 1,250 gp for the raise dead spell is paid for by the party at the end of the session. Other characters are under no obligation to spend their funds to bring back a dead party member. </P>

<P>Faction Charity. If the character is of level 1 to 4 and a member of a faction, the dead character’s body can be returned to civilization and a patron from the faction ensures that he or she receives a raise dead spell. However, any character invoking this charity forfeits all XP and rewards from that session (even those earned prior to death during that session), and cannot replay that episode or adventure with that character again. Once a character reaches 5th level, this option is no longer available.  </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Part>

<Part>
<H2>Adventure Background </H2>

<P>In its quest to set Tiamat free in the world, the Cult of the Dragon is ever searching for magical knowledge and spares no effort in doing so. Cult leaders enlisted the aid of expatriate Red Wizards of Thay, who hoped eventually to turn Tiamat's power against Szass Tam. </P>

<P>Those Red Wizards are assigned to wide-ranging tasks across Faer. Dues for the Dead concerns a Red Wizard necromancer named Rorreth Monforoth who was assigned to find a way to locate the now-inert Pool of Radiance beneath Phlan and reconnect it to the Weave. </P>

<P>At some point, long ago, a Pool of Radiance—a powerful and dangerous anomaly in the Weave—formed beneath Phlan, a city with a long and troubled history on the northern shore of the Moonsea. This font of raw magic was found by an entity named Tyranthraxus who used its power to possess the body of a bronze dragon. Tyranthraxus was eventually defeated by a band of adventurers and the Pool of Radiance was transformed into a normal pool of water beneath Valjevo Castle. Despite this, however, its legend persists. </P>

<P>Rorreth Monforoth has been sent to Phlan along with a handful of Cult &quot;advisors&quot; for two reasons; to seek out a means of entry into the ruins beneath Valjevo Castle and to create a host of undead. Once this has been accomplished, the Cult will have a veritable army of undead with which to secure Phlan, and subsequently, the Pool of Radiance. </P>
</Part>

<Part>
<H2>Overview </H2>

<P>The adventure begins with characters hearing about the reappearance of undead creatures in the cemetery next to the city of Phlan. The faithful of Kelemvor, who take care of the cemetery, are seeking men and women who are willing to track down the undead, destroy them, and find out where they came from and why. </P>

<P>Most of the cemetery is underground, in extensive catacombs that have been used for more than a millennia. They are provided a guide, but not even the cemetery's caretakers know the full extent of the catacombs. Much of the adventure involves exploring the catacombs, facing revived undead and other dangers, until characters discover that a Red Wizard necromancer is responsible for the trouble. They capture a clue about what the necromancer seeks, and they can gain important additional information if they take that clue to an NPC sage for analysis. </P>

<P>Armed with solid information about the necromancer's goal, the adventurers set out to confront him to prevent him from achieving his goal. </P>

<P>Dues for the Dead </P>
</Part>

<Part>
<Sect>
<H2>Adventure Hook </H2>

<P>While the characters are in the city of Phlan or traveling nearby, they encounter this handbill posted on a wall or tree. They could also hear the information directly in conversation with a traveling merchant or a resident of Phlan or overhear other travelers discussing &quot;the undead problem&quot; at Valhingen Graveyard. </P>

<P>WANTED: Holy Knights, Blessed Warriors of the Gods, and other bold slayers of the Undead. Reward commensurate with risk. For particulars, contact Doomguide Yovir Glandon at Valhingen Graveyard, City of Phlan </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H4>Valhingen Graveyard </H4>

<P>The graveyard sits north of the city, on the opposite shore of Stojanow River. It is a beautiful garden of statues, tended plants, trees, mausoleums, and headstones. The condition of the graveyard is entirely pristine thanks to the tireless work of Kelemvorites who tend it. </P>

<P>Phlan has been the site of a city for over 1,000 years. It's experienced so many cycles of growth and collapse, of prosperity and destruction, that it's impossible to estimate accurately how many people have lived there and subsequently been interred in Valhingen. A conservative estimate puts the number at well over 100,000 but that estimate could easily be two, three, or even five times that many. </P>

<P>Valhingen is large, but so many bodies couldn't possibly be buried there in individual graves and family mausoleums. Most of them are interred in catacombs beneath the graveyard. The catacombs are nearly as old as the city, and their full extent is unknown even to the most senior of Kelemvorites. They extend well beyond the boundary of the graveyard in every direction, including under the city. </P>

<P>Several of the major temples and fortifications in Phlan were known to have entrances of their own, but most of these were sealed during times when undead were a threat. If any of them remain open, no one living in Phlan today knows of them. The only entrance that's known to still be open is the Cloister of Kelemvor in Valhingen Graveyard, and only those galleries directly connected to it are still used for burials. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H5>The City of Phlan </H5>

<P>The bulk of the action in Dues for the Dead takes place under </P>

<P>Valhingen Graveyard. Characters might spend a short time in </P>

<P>the city proper, however, when they first arrive or if they consult </P>

<P>with a sage during the adventure. In that case, you'll want some </P>

<P>basic, atmospheric information on the city. </P>

<P>Phlan has a thousand-year history of ascendance and </P>

<P>collapse. Currently, it's experiencing tough times. Less than a </P>

<P>year ago, the city's Lord Protector Anivar Daoran was killed in </P>

<P>an apparent construction accident while inspecting renovations </P>

<P>at Valjevo Castle. Daoran wasn't much of a Lord Protector and </P>

<P>he isn't widely mourned. Because he left no heir, the Knight </P>

<P>Commander of the Black Fist, Ector Brahms, was declared the </P>

<P>Lord Regent. Brahms is an honorable but hidebound man, and </P>

<P>Phlan has declined tragically under his guidance. Soldiers of the </P>

<P>Black Fist rule the city by martial law. They swiftly dispense </P>

<P>punishment but seldom justice. Their increasingly harsh </P>

<P>methods are failing to preserve law or order. </P>

<P>Without the Black Fist to protect them, the people have </P>

<P>turned to two other sources; the city's guilds (chiefly </P>

<P>stonewrights, carpenters, ironhands, and merchants) and a </P>

<P>criminal organization called the Welcomers. These six </P>

<P>organizations are constantly at odds with one another over </P>

<P>power in the city and, aside from limited exceptions among the </P>

<P>guilds, are completely unable to cooperate for the betterment of </P>

<P>Phlan. Lord Protector Daoran had begun many construction </P>

<P>projects around the city, renovating ancient buildings and </P>

<P>reconstructing those damaged in recent wars. All of that work is </P>

<P>halted since the city has no money to pay the guilds for their </P>

<P>labor; half-built structures are everywhere and heaps of unused </P>

<P>construction material clog the streets. </P>

<P>Trade, too, has come to a standstill, leaving merchants with </P>

<P>few legal ways to make a living. The Welcomers are openly </P>

<P>criminal, and the once-honest guilds are only a few steps </P>

<P>removed from being organized crime syndicates themselves. </P>

<P>The Black Fist's methods have made it the people's enemy </P>

<P>instead of their guardian, so most honest folk have retreated </P>

<P>into the ranks of the Welcomers and the guilds for survival.  </P>

<P>Dues for the Dead </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>T ssits north of thee river. Most of the city is on wwhat's ppresumed to bee an artificial island; sometimee in the dim ppast, Phlan's orriginal builderss dug a canal too split the SStojanow Riverr into two channels at its mouuth, with the twwo branches fllowing around the city like a mmoat. A bbridge near the city's North Gate crosses thee river a sshort distance wwest of the gravveyard, so mouurners can wwalk to the cemmetery easily. </P>

<P>The cemeteryy itself is quite beautiful. </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_2.jpg"/>
Part G The graveyard i t 1: Va Grave is the only nota alhing eyard able feature of P gen Phlan that </Figure>

<P>VValhingen Graveyyard looks more like a park than a cemetery aand stands in staark contrast to thhe ramshackle, haalf-built PPhlan. Gravel walkways wend between tall trees, wwell-tended bbeds of shrubs annd flowers, sturddy mausoleums, and rows of hheadstones, monnuments, and commemorative sttatues. </P>

<P>You need only aa few moments too spot a man and a woman ddressed in simplee, home-spun gray robes trimminng shrubs aand pulling weeds from between gravestones. </P>

<P>TThe man and wwoman are cleriics of Kelemvor named DDrolo and Fedyya. They are haappy to talk aboout their wwork in the cemmetery, but theyy grow morose if asked aabout undead. IInstead, they diirect characters to a small cchapel where DDoomguide Yovvir Glandon cann be found. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H5>KKelemvor's Faaithful </H5>

<P>DDoomguide is thee title adopted byy heads of clericaal chapters aamong the faithfu<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_3.jpg"/>
ul of Kelemvor, FF</Figure>
aern's deity of ddeath and the ddead. &quot;Doom&quot; reffers not to a bleaak destiny but simmply to the fafact that all mortaals face an end too life. Kelemvor'ss servants eensure that the deead are properly interred and respected, and they see to the neeeds of the bereaved. To most of Kelemvor's fafaithful, raising a dead person as aan undead creatuure is the mmost horrific sacrrilege imaginablee and an unforgivvable violation oof human sanctityy. </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_4.jpg"/>
</Figure>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>TThe Doommguide's Tale </H3>

<P>FFinding Doomgguide Glandon is simple enouugh. Yovir GGlandon is a huuman male of mmiddle age, hummorless and sstoic in his dutyy among the deead. </P>

<P>Doomguuide Yovir Glanddon is a thin, humman male of midddle age, withh a shaved head and a well-trimmmed beard, streaaked with greey. He is dressed in a grass-stained gray robe with twigs and leavves tangled around the frayed hem, sweeping leaaves out of thhe simple stone chapel with a woorn-out broom.</P>

<P> As you approach, he sttops sweeping annd turns his deepp-set, blue eyees in your directioon. </P>

<P> “Hello there,” he says iin a surprisingly resonant voice, “What service ccan Kelemvor’s FFaithful provide for you today?”f </P>

<Sect>
<H5>Rolepllaying Doommguide Glandon </H5>

<P>Yovir Glandon has toiledd in the gardens oof Valhingen for nearly </P>

<P><Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_5.jpg"/>
40 yearss. But despite his</Figure>
s dirty, calloused hands and his grass-stained robes, he is a leaarned man. Yovirr is a reserved maan, who letss others steer thee course of a conversation; interjeecting only wheere necessary. </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_6.jpg"/>
</Figure>

<P>Yovir prrefers to let chharacters bring up the subject of the handbilll or rumors of undead themsselves, rather thhan asking them if they'ree mercenaries looking for worrk (that fact should be obbvious to anyonne who glancess at the heaavily armed andd armored charracters). Once aasked, he relattes the followinng tale. During the course of ttheir converssation, Yovir prrovides the following informaation: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Soome of the adveenturers may know Doomguidde Yoovir from DDEXX1-3 Shadows over the Moonnsea. If thiis is the case, YYovir is especiaally pleased to ssee theem again. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Wiithin the last 1000 years, Valhiingen Graveyarrd has gonne from being overrun with uundead to the sttatuesqque place of resst it is today. TThis is due primmarily to tthe work of thee Kelemvoritess. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Too the people of PPhlan, the idylllic beauty of Vaalhingen is theirr reward for thhe trials they haave facced during theirr hard life wheen it is over. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>A nnovice Kelemvoorite disappearred about a moonth agoo. Yovir was innitially unconceerned as the lifee of a Keelemvorite is diifficult, and thoose who cannott accommmodate it simmply leave. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Suuspicions were aroused when Brother Rasorran— anoother Kelemvoorite—vanishedd. It was not posssible thaat he would leaave; he has beenn dedicated to the faitth and to the people of Phlan for nearly 10 yyears. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Sisster Bethel disaappeared and wwas subsequenntly loccated twelve daays ago; partiallly eaten. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Yoovir believes thaat undead are aactive once more witthin Valhingenn. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Yoovir and a few oother Kelemvorrites investigateed the olddest section of tthe known cataacombs and fouund no  undead. It wass sealed to prevvent them spreeading </LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H4>Duees for the DDead </H4>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>inside. </P>

<P>If the adventureers appear interested in taking the job, YYovir provides tthe following innformation. </P>

<P> He can payy the characterss 100 gp and aa set of goggles of nighht.  If the advennturers ask forr an advance to pay for supplies, he instead givess them the gogggles of night. </P>

<P> Yovir asks that the adventurers do not ddisturb the resting deaad within the caatacombs and tto leave their possessionns be. Theft fromm the dead is nnot tolerated. </P>

<P> The catacoombs are extensive, and Yovirr offers the adventurerrs the services oof a guide if theey so desire one. </P>

<P>If the adventureers accept Yoviir’s offer of a guuide, Yovir ccalls out “Cassyyt!”, and a younng woman nammed Cassyt sshuffles into thee room. She is a plain-lookingg female hhalf-elf who apppears to be in hher early twentiies. She uuses the acolyte stat block. Beesides acting ass guide, CCassyt also carrries a lantern to help light thee tunnels, uunless characteers prefer darknness. Cassyt knnows as mmuch of the hisstory of the cataacombs as you want him or hher to tell the chharacters. </P>

<P>Cassyt assist the party usingg cantrips whenn able to do sso from range, bbut flees if confronted by an eenemy. She ddoes not use heer first level speell slots until thhe final eencounter in Arrea 14b. </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_7.jpg"/>
CCassyt is a youngg</Figure>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H5>RRoleplaying Cassyt </H5>

<P> Kelemvorite whoo has spent more time in her bbooks than in thee catacombs of thhe graveyard. Despite this, she hhas an unusually sunny dispositioon and is prone to chatter inncessantly rattlinng off minutiae and trivia about thhe catacombs. </P>

<P>She knows quite aa bit about Sectioons 1 through 3 of the </P>

<P>atacombs (Histoory +4; catacombbs only) and first aid (Medicine </P>

<P>+3). She also has a dry, albeit slightly warped, sense of humor. </P>
</Sect>
<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_8.jpg"/>
S c + c</Figure>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H4>TTreasure </H4>

<P>If they ask, the adventurers arre given a pair oof goggles of nnight to assist them with theirr excursion. </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_9.jpg"/>
</Figure>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H4>Duees for the DDead </H4>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>T sstructure that reesembles the mmany mausoleuums in the ggraveyard, exceept this buildingg has no door, jjust an open aarchway. Insidee is a small pavved floor that oppens into a wwide stone stairrcase. The buillding is little moore than a ccovering over thhe stairs. Dwarrves can easily see that the sstone building iis much newer than the steps; the walls aand roof have stood for no moore than two centuries, but thhe steps are at least four timees that old; posssibly even oolder.  </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>GGeneral Featuress </H3>
<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_10.jpg"/>
Part C The entrance to t 2: Th Catac o the catacomb he Upp ombs bs is through a s per stone </Figure>

<P>NNote that the mmap is labeled wwith north at the bottom aand south at thee top. This is soo you can moree easily draw itt correctly for tthe players withhout needing too continually flflip it upside doown. </P>

<P>Ceilings and Walls. Althouggh the catacommbs are all eexcavated fromm earth and solidd stone, the tunnnels look nnothing like a mmine. Most wallls and ceilings are either fafaced with smooth stone or haave decorative ffeatures ssuch as faux pilllars, ledges, geeometric designns, and sscenes of life orr religious themmes carved intoo the stone. UUnless otherwise specified, thhe ceilings of thhe ccatacombs are only 10 feet higgh. </P>

<P>Crypts. Most individual cryppts are not desccribed, bbecause they'ree all basically thhe same. The wwalls are ccarved with locuuli (niches) thaat contain eitheer a single bbody or the staccked bones of mmany bodies. MMost of these ccrypts aren't very interesting; they contain noo treasure, nno monsters, annd no clues. Moost of the bodiees in a pparticular cryptt are related somehow. Usuallly they're of thhe same familyy, but customs changed over tthe ccenturies: somee crypts containn members of tthe same gguild, or peoplee of the same agge, or people wwho died of thhe same causees or who serveed in the same mmilitary uunits. Characters should be leess interested inn what's innside individuaal crypts than bby what's happeening in the tuunnels around them. </P>

<P>Light. The caatacombs are coompletely darkk except wwhere noted. NNiches are carveed into the wallls every 20 fefeet for placemeent of oil lampss, but lamps areen't left in thhe niches. Thee faithful of Keleemvor bring lammps with thhem when theyy come into thee catacombs. Inn a few pplaces, open shhafts have been dug from the ccatacombs to the surface too let in air and light. These arre noted in </P>
</Sect>

<P>Not for resale. Peermission granted to print or photo </P>

<Sect>
<P>text andd on the map. </P>

<P>Sounnd. The catacommbs deaden soound effectivelyy. For lack of a better phrasee, the catacombbs are, for the mmost part, ass silent as the ggrave. Occasionnally, dripping wwater can be heard. Open shhafts for lettingg in air and lighht sometimmes produce uunsettling akin mmoaning or whistlinng on windy daays. It is not unheard of to heaar distant crying while inn the catacombbs, but it is attriibuted to thosee on in the gravveyard, above, mourning theirr dead insteadd of any malevoolence within thhe catacombs. </P>

<P>Undeead. The faithfuul of Kelemvorr cleared all thee undeadd out of these caatacombs decaades ago and keept the tunnnels clear sincee then. Howeveer, due to the ssheer size of tthe catacombs, the Red Wizaard Rorreth Monforroth has had pllenty of time to animate undeaad creaturres from the cryypts before theeir presence waas prematturely discovereed. Monforoth can't control alll the undeadd he created, annd some of themm strayed into areas of the ccatacombs thatt allowed their ddiscovery </P>

<P>Wateer. Most of the tunnels and cryrypts stay dry. TThere are pudddles or even kknee-deep water in some sectiions that strray beneath thee Stojanow River. </P>

<P>Gatess. The gates arre of sturdy andd relatively neww construuction. Unless ootherwise speccified, the gatess are locked and require a sset of thieves' ttools and a successsful DC 15 Dexxterity check too open. The gattes may bee forced open wwith a successfuul DC 15 Strenngth check. DDoing so makees an obscene aamount of noisse, howeveer. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>1. Clloister oof Kelemvvor </H3>

<P>The firsst chamber thee adventurers eenter is the Cloiister. </P>

<P>The base of the stairs oppens into a largee, irregularly-shapped chambeer. Stone ledges aare carved along most of the walls to serve ass tables. </P>

<P> The farr wall of this roomm is covered a huge fresco. The painted tiles portraying people from every race and walkk of life, arrangedd with no sense of perspective or relative scale. TThe design hhas suffered heavvy damage from water seepage aand mildew over the centuriees. </P>

<P>The reccently deceasedd can be placedd on any of several stone bbiers for viewing by family meembers and frieends before tthey are carried deeper into tthe catacombs for intermeent. </P>

<P>Anyone who examinnes the fresco aand succeeds aat a </P>

<P>DC 15 Intelligence (Innvestigation) chheck sees it forr what </P>

<P>it truly iis—a century-oold map of the ccatacombs. Thiis is </P>

<P>hard too recognize, howwever, due to thhe damage andd the </P>

<P>Duees for the DDead </P>
</Sect>

<P>copy this document for personal usse only. 9 </P>

<Sect>
<P>lack of any consistent scale. </P>

<P>Areas 1 and 2 are typically as far as non-faithful folk ever come into the catacombs. Typically, only the members of the clergy are permitted beyond this point. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>2. Funerary Banquet Hall </H3>

<P>Many families hold funeral banquets when their loved ones are interred. Middle class and wealthy families prefer to rent a banquet room in an inn or host the banquet in their homes, but the faithful of Kelemvor don't charge for use of this room (labeled “a” on the map), so it's popular with poorer families in Phlan. </P>

<P>This banquet hall is surprisingly pleasant when considering its location. Many colored lanterns and small incense burners are lit. The long tables are boards lain over a pair of trestles fashioned of wood planks, with benches for seating. </P>

<P>A smaller room in the southern corner of the hall is sealed with a locked iron gate. </P>

<P>What at first appears to be a small room or closet turns out to be reveals a shaft down to another chamber. A set of block and tackle hang from the ceiling of the shaft, and handholds have been chiseled into the wall. </P>

<P>This shaft descends into a chamber (labeled “b” on the map) used by the clergy to prepare bodies for interment. Hanging from the top of the shaft is a set of block and tackle; likely for lowering dead bodies to the chamber below. </P>

<P>From this room, there is a small door on the northeastern corner that leads to area 13. The door is locked but may be opened with the same key that unlocked the gate in area 2a, or with a successful DC 15 Dexterity check using thieves’ tools. The gate may be forced open with a successful DC 15 Strength check. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>3. First Families of Phlan </H3>

<P>These crypts are reserved for the wealthy and the powerful: successful merchants, political leaders, military officers, and their families. They have an almost museum-like quality. </P>

<P>This series of crypts has doorways sealed by locked iron grates. Within you see scenes of normal daily life: richly-dressed people seated around dining tables, or at writing desks, or in luxurious chairs. </P>

<P>All of this would be completely normal, except that all of the participants in the macabre dioramas are the skeletal remains of the affluent—carefully posed and interred among their favorite possessions. </P>

<P>Because of this area's attraction to thieves, every iron grate is double-locked and warded. Doomguide Yovir Glandon has the only keys for the locks. Picking a lock requires a successful DC 15 Dexterity check using a set of thieves’ tools. </P>

<P>Opening or attempting to open one of the locks with anything other than the proper key sets off a magicmouth spell that intones, &quot;Think twice on what you are about to do, friend. Your trespass has been noted.&quot;  In fact, there is no other alarm and the magic mouth spell doesn't alert the faithful of Kelemvor to the break-in. </P>

<P>Treasure </P>

<P>If the characters decide to break in to the crypts, they can collect 40 gp worth of easily-pocketed jewelry, and another 60 gp worth of bulky, but valuable, clothing from each. </P>

<P>The Kelemvorites, however, notice within a few days should any small items be taken. And as the catacombs have recently been sealed, the adventurers are likely the prime suspects. </P>

<P>The Kelemvorites notice characters trying removing bulky items from the catacombs immediately upon exiting. </P>

<P>Cassyt will inform Doomguide Glandon if she sees any of the adventurers take any of the treasure belonging to the dead. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>4. The Bone Pit </H3>

<P>The faithful of Kelemvor don't know why some bones were thrown here while others were stored more respectfully in loculi and orderly ossuaries. In fact, this pit was used long ago by one of the more macabre funerary cults (see area 5). </P>

<P>Dues for the Dead </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>A circular pit nearly fills this chamber, leaving only a foot-wide pathway between the edge of the pit and the wall. The pit is filled to about five feet below the lip with humanoid bones. A narrow walkway hugging the walls is the only path through the chamber. </P>

<P>Narrow niches in the walls are filled with carefully placed bones, baubles, and other similar items. </P>

<P>The encircling pathway is only about a foot wide. To walk the path without falling into the pit requires a successful DC 5 Dexterity (Acrobatics) check. Falling into the jagged bones in the pit causes 3 (1d6) points of piercing damage.  </P>

<P>Falling into the pit and the subsequent struggle to get out makes enough noise to alert the ghouls who are hiding in area 5. If the adventurers end up not proceeding into area 5, their presence is known by the ghouls, who stalk them and attack them during their next fight. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>5. Funerary Cults </H3>

<P>Over the centuries, a handful of exclusive funerary cults have flourished in Phlan. This section of the catacombs was reserved for their use. (The pit in area 4 was the work of one of these cults.) One room contains row upon row of pottery animals that were made from the ashes and ground bones of the deceased. Another contains thousands upon thousands of disarticulated bones hanging by thin wires from the ceiling so that no two bones touch each other.  </P>

<P>The only important chamber here is one that smells powerfully of smoke; it contains many dozens of bodies preserved by the smoke from aromatic charcoal burned in iron braziers (now unlit). The corpses are well preserved but jet black. </P>

<P>The smell of wood smoke is overpowering in this room, and every surface is stained jet black with soot that must have come from the two great iron braziers on the floor. The walls are lined with almost perfectly preserved bodies—black from the same soot that stains the walls. They might almost be mistaken for mummified drow were it not for the different colors of hair. </P>

<P>Several corpses, however, have been ravaged by something. They lay in the center of the room, torn apart, their flesh and bones gnawed by some ravenous creature. </P>

<P>The preserved bodies drew two hungry ghouls to this area, and they're still present, hidden among the </P>

<P>corpses. They hid among the bodies when they heard the characters approaching (make a single Dexterity (Stealth) check with a +4 bonus). Any adventurer who’s passive Wisdom (Perception) score exceeds the result of their Dexterity (Stealth) check notices the ghouls. </P>

<P>Upon realizing that they have been discovered, the ghouls attack. Otherwise, they attack at the most advantageous moment if no one spots them. If the adventurers do not venture further into the room, the ghouls attempt to stalk the adventurers and attack them during their next fight. </P>

<P>“Well, that about does it for me. You know I don’t get paid for this, right?” --Cassyt </P>

<P>Adjusting the Encounter </P>

<P>Here are recommendations for adjusting this combat </P>

<P>encounter. These are not cumulative. </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Very weak party: remove one ghoul </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Weak party: change one ghoul to a zombie </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Strong party: add one ghoul </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Very strong party: add three ghouls </LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>6. Rickety Stairs </H3>

<P>The passage descends by shallow stone steps to a 15-foot by 15-foot square room. Wooden stairs wind around the walls of the shaft down into the darkness. </P>

<P>The stairs look as though they are ancient, and the wood rotted and weak. </P>

<P>They wind around a tall statue of a strange, four-armed humanoid with vaguely insectoid features. It clutches a scroll in one hand, a quill in a second, a skull in a third, while the fourth is empty. </P>

<P>The floor of the room is about 20 feet below that of the hallway leading into it, and the steps are about 3 feet wide. The stairs are also on the verge of collapse. Each character who uses the steps must make a DC 10 Dexterity (Acrobatics) check at the midpoint of the stairs as they descend or ascend. An unsuccessful check causes 5 points of damage to the stairs. If the check succeeds, no damage is dealt to the stairs. </P>

<P>Describe the creaking, cracking, and groaning from the ancient wood, and the dust that falls with every step. The staircase collapses when it accumulates 10 points of damage, dropping everyone on it to the floor of the room. Any character who is on the stairs when they collapse suffers 7 (2d6) bludgeoning damage and falls prone. </P>

<P>Dues for the Dead </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>The noise of tthe collapsing sstairs draws thhe attention oof the zombies in Area 7 who come to investigate the ddisturbance. </P>

<P>On the plus side, the collapsse leaves plentyy of hhandholds and footholds wherre wooden posts were set innto the stone, sso the walls cann be climbed wwith a ssuccessful DC 110 Strength (Athletics) check. The DC of thhis check is lowwered to 5 if thhe adventurers also use a rrope to climb. </P>

<P>Any adventurrer succeeding at a DC 15 Inteelligence (RReligion) checkk identifies thee statue at the bbottom as thhat of Jergal, ann ancient deityy charged with rrecording thhe disposition of the souls annd guarding thee tombs of thhe dead. </P>

<P>“A“And how do you expect me to gget down?!” --Cassyt </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H4>TTreasure </H4>

<P>TThe statues eyees are two piecees of flawless jeet worth 25 ggp each. </P>

<P>Cassyt will innform Doomguiide Glandon if sshe sees any oof the adventureers take either of the gems. <Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_11.jpg"/>
</Figure>
</P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H4>Duees for the DDead </H4>
</Sect>
<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_12.jpg"/>
Part C The catacombs t 3. Th Catac s beyond this po he Low ombs oint are hundre wer eds of years </Figure>

<Sect>
<P>T oold and startingg to show their age. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H5>LLoose Brickwwork </H5>
</Sect>

<P>TThe walls and ceilings of this section of the catacoombs are old <Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_13.jpg"/>
c hey collapse. If ar. While damageect, the intense ves, under certain cv</Figure>
aand in poor repai d walls or ceilingg won't collapse under noormal conditions circumstances, t a character casts thunderwave or aanother ability wwith a similar effe ibrations trigger a collapse. FFalling stoneworkk causes 4 (1d8) bludgeoning dammage to each </P>

<P><Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_14.jpg"/>
cc</Figure>
reature in the room where the sppell is cast. This ddamage is hhalved if the creatture succeeds at a DC 10 Dexteritty saving throw. </P>

<Sect><Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_15.jpg"/>
</Figure>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>77A. Sun PPit </H3>

<P>TThis room was used as a means of destroyinng vampires. VVampires were staked and shackled to the wwall. When thhe morning sun rose, it wouldd eventually shhine down thhrough the graates above, desttroying the vammpires. </P>

<P>TThis square roomm is approximately 20 feet across. The ceiling, fafar above, is cappped with iron graates through whicch the sky aabove can be seeen. </P>

<P>Shackles are bolted to the walls and an iron lockkbox is fafastened to the wwall. The lid to thee lockbox is openn, revealing a nnumber of woodeen stakes. </P>

<P>Though it is diffficult to be sure, a hinged gate in the grate aabove seems to bbe open and a lenngth of rope endding in a ggrappling hook laays in a heap on the floor in frontt of you bbeside a short, ruusted iron bar. </P>

<P>AA group of four zombies are inn this room, haaving been aattracted by thee noise made byy the would-be thieves. </P>

<P>A couple of thhieves have brooken into the caatacombs. WWhen the last oof them was climmbing down, thhe bar that thhe grappling hook was hanginng from broke loose and ssent one of themm falling the last 10 feet and wworse yet, aalerting a pack of zombies to ttheir presence. They took rrefuge in Area 77b. When the aadventurers arrrive, the zzombies are banging on the dooor that the Weelcomers hhave barricadedd themselves behind. They atttack the aadventurers shoould any of them enter this Arrea. </P>
</Sect>

<P>Not for resale. Peermission granted to print or photo </P>

<Sect>
<H5>Adjustting the Enccounter </H5>

<P>Here aree recommendatioons for adjustingg this combat er. These are not cumulative. </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_16.jpg"/>
encountt </Figure>

<P> Veryy weak or weak pparty: remove twoo zombies </P>

<P><Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_17.jpg"/>
Stro he beginning of tthe second round </Figure>
ong party: two additional zombiess wander into thee room at th d </P>

<P> Veryy strong party: a ghoul wanders innto the room at tthe begi<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_18.jpg"/>
inning of the secc</Figure>
ond round </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_19.jpg"/>
</Figure>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>7B. CCrematoria Niches </H3>

<P>This rooom is used to hhouse people wwhose remains have been crremated; a pracctice that only rrecently came iinto fashionn. </P>

<P>Unbeeknownst to thee Kelemvoritess, a group of thiieves have stoolen into the caatacombs amiddst the disruptiion caused by the appearaance of undeadd. </P>

<P>The wallls of this long rooom bear hundreeds upon hundreeds of niches; mmost of which bear a small urn oor box, and a trinnket or two.</P>

<P> An elf, a tiefling and a hhiccupping half-oorc crouch on thhe far side of tthe room, clutching swords in their shaking handds. </P>

<P>A trio oof Welcomers——a half-orc spy, an elf bandit, and a tiefling bandit—have ttaken refuge inn this area. Specificcally chosen foor the job becauuse they possesss darkvission, they originnally snuck intoo the catacombbs two days aggo to investigate the rumors oof undead, but couldn''t resist pilferinng some of the items in the rooom. By the ttime they realizzed that their aactivities attraccted the atteention of some roaming zombbies, it was too late; they baarred the door aand have been waiting here evver since. </P>

<P>They planned ratheer poorly and beetween them had </P>

<P>only a ssingle flask of rrather potent wwhiskey. Upon </P>

<P>realizinng that they werre trapped, thee half-orc spy reefused </P>

<P>to sharee the whiskey wwith the elf andd the tiefling, annd </P>

<P>has beeen well-and-truly drunk ever ssince. The </P>

<P>Welcommers are initiallly relieved to foound by the parrty </P>

<P>and begg the adventureers for whateveer food or wateer they </P>

<P>have. TThe half-orc is ddoubly pleased and offers everryone </P>

<P>within rreach an awkwward (and ratheer smelly) hug. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Plunddered Treaasures </H4>

<P>Any chaaracter succeedding at a DC 10 Wisdom (Percepption) check nootices that eachh of the Welcommers has a feew trinkets stufffed into their ppockets. The adventuurers can persuuade the Welcoomers into leavving the treaasures behind wwith a successfful DC 15 Charrisma (Intimiddation or Persuuasion). If unsuuccessful, nothiing short off force is goingg to deter them from abscondiing </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H4>Duees for the DDead </H4>
</Sect>

<P>copy this document for personal usse only. 13 </P>

<Sect>
<P>with the treasure. </P>

<P>If it comes to blows and any of the Welcomers are killed in the struggle, the adventurers receive the Enmity of the Welcomers (see Favors and Enmity, below). </P>

<P>Cassyt will inform Doomguide Glandon if she sees any of the adventurers take any of the treasure belonging to the dead. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H4>Helping the Welcomers Escape </H4>

<P>The Welcomers want to leave the catacombs, preferably via the way they entered as they do not want the Kelemvorites knowing that they were down here. However, if faced with choosing between leaving out the front door and staying in the catacombs, they choose the former and upon leaving the catacombs are confronted by the Kelemvorites. Cassyt urges the party not to help them sneak out, but can be persuaded to turn a blind eye with a successful DC 10 Charisma (Persuasion) check. </P>

<P>If the adventurers decide to help the Welcomers sneak out, they not only need to secure a line up, but they also need to come up with a way to get the half-orc out as he is clearly in no state to make the climb. The adventurers can use the grappling hook and hook it to the grate above with a successful DC 15 Strength or Dexterity check. </P>

<P>Once the grappling hook is secure or the adventurers have otherwise secured a rope to the grate above, the elf and the tiefling climb out with no problem. The half-orc can't, however, and needs to be hauled up. Because they are not on the best of terms with the stingy half-orc, the elf and the tiefling are unwilling to wait for him to sober up. They will provide a limited amount of help to the adventurers to haul the half-orc up if they ask for it.  </P>

<P>Between the three of them, they possess the following equipment: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Three, 50 ft. lengths of hempen rope; </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Two sets of thieves' tools; </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>A bag of ball bearings; and </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>A nearly empty flask of rather potent whiskey. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Allow the players to get creative with how they would like to try and get the half-orc up. The easiest way would require a block and tackle. Thankfully, there is one in area 2. If the adventurers do not remember the block and tackle, any adventurer succeeding at a DC 10 Intelligence check remembers seeing the block and tackle. If the adventurers think to ask Cassyt, she thinks for a moment and then remembers that the Kelemvorites use one in area 2 to lower bodies into the catacombs. </P>

<P>A character must succeed on two successive DC 15 Strength checks in order to hoist the half-orc spy up to the grate above. If they are using the block and tackle from area 2, this check is made with advantage. The elf and the tiefling refuse to help pull. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Cassyt </H4>

<P>If the adventurers help the Welcomers sneak out, Cassyt is naturally upset. However, she is young and relatively naïve, and can be persuaded to keep mum about it with a successful DC 10 Charisma (Persuasion) check. Feel free to award advantage on this check for especially creative roleplaying. </P>

<P>&quot; Doomguide Glandon isn't going to be pleased to hear about this…&quot; </P>

<P>--Cassyt </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Treasure </H4>

<P>The Welcomers have looted a total of 80 gp in various types of plundered trinkets and art objects. They also carry 20 gp in coins of their own. </P>

<P>An additional 50 gp worth of coins and trinkets can be further pilfered from the niches that the Welcomers didn't empty. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>8. Obelisk </H3>

<P>The walls of this semi-circular chamber are lined with nearly a hundred loculi, each containing the bones of one or more deceased residents of Phlan. An obelisk stands in the center of the chamber. Its four faces are covered in mysterious runes. </P>

<P>The carvings are in Celestial and use its intricate, flowing script. If no one in the party understands Celestial, the language can be identified only with at least a minute's study and a successful DC 15 Intelligence (History) check. The writing is not terribly interesting; it speaks in general terms about the goodly lives of those interred in the chamber. </P>

<P>The corridor continues to the east and down a set of stairs. </P>

<P>Dues for the Dead </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>9. Skeletal Ceiling </H3>

<P>The walls in this section are lined with burial niches containing skeletons, as in other areas of the catacombs, but skeletons also stare down at you from the ceiling where they were set into shallow plaster. Some arm bones, leg bones, and skulls have cracked free and fallen to the floor, but most remain in the positions and poses they were given ages ago. </P>

<P>Rorreth Monforoth animated five skeletons in the ceiling as guardians where they've remained quietly in the ceiling for more than a week. As the adventurers pass beneath them, the skeletons break free from the plaster and drop down to attack. Stage this situation for maximum drama among your players. It might be most effective, for example, to have only half the skeletons drop down on the first round. On the second and third rounds, more can drop into the fight in locations where they directly threaten characters who try to avoid melee, such as spellcasters and archers. </P>

<P>Adjusting the Encounter </P>

<P>Here are recommendations for adjusting this combat </P>

<P>encounter. These are not cumulative. </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Very weak party: remove three skeletons </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Weak party: remove two skeletons </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Strong party: add one skeleton; all living creatures in the </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>room take 4 (1d8) points of slashing damage from jagged </P>

<P>chunks of plaster when the skeletons break loose. Creatures </P>

<P>who succeed at a DC 11 Dexterity saving throw take no </P>

<P>damage. </P>

<P> Very strong party: add two skeletons; all living creatures in </P>

<P>the room take 4 (1d8) points of slashing and bludgeoning </P>

<P>damage from jagged chunks of plaster when the skeletons </P>

<P>break loose. Creatures who succeed at a DC 11 Dexterity </P>

<P>saving throw take no damage. </P>

<P>“Gah!” </P>

<P>--Cassyt </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>10. The Tomb of Sedrair II </H3>

<P>A mummified figure in magnificent apparel sits on a throne inlaid with ivory and semiprecious stones. It holds a golden dagger in its right hand and a balance in its left. A crown of gold and tarnished silver seems to float above its head. The whole scene is draped in cobwebs. </P>

<P>In life, this was Sedrair II, one of the richer (and more eccentric) grander nobles of Phlan centuries ago. Paranoid even in death, her crown is warded against theft by a clever glyph. </P>

<P>The balance is the type with two pans suspended from a lightweight beam. A secret compartment in the chair holds a box of weights; the compartment can be noticed with a successful DC 15 Wisdom (Perception) check. The scales are not in balance when the adventurers arrive, due to the accumulation of dust and debris over the ages, but it really doesn’t matter—rebalancing the pans with the hidden weights or anything else does nothing. </P>

<P>The crown is not floating above the skull but is suspended by thin wires ending in small hooks. Cobwebs camouflage the wires; they are noticed only by adventurers who succeed at a DC 15 Wisdom (Perception) check. </P>

<P>The wires are linked to the glyph, which is triggered if the weight on the wires increases or decreases by more than a few ounces. The trap is a glyph of warding that causes 9 (2d8) lightning damage to everyone in the chamber; a successful DC 13 Dexterity saving throw halves the damage. </P>

<P>Clever characters might try to neutralize the trap using the weights from the throne. This can be done, but it's tricky. With a successful DC 20 Dexterity (Sleight of Hand) check, the crown can be removed by replacing it with weights. A successful DC 15 Intelligence (Investigation) check beforehand allows the adventurer to approximate the weight of the crown; granting advantage on the Dexterity check. Failure on the Dexterity check sets off the trap. </P>

<P>“Not that you would listen to me anyway, I just thought you should know that Sedrair was quite fond of her gold. She probably wouldn’t appreciate your mucking about with it.” </P>

<P>--Cassyt </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H4>Treasure </H4>

<P>Sedrair's crown is worth 250 gp if it's recovered without setting off the trap; if the trap goes off, damage from the lightning reduces its value to just 50 gp. The fine set of weights is worth 120 gp if complete and the balance accompanies it. The weights alone are worth 80 gp if complete or 10 gp if some of the weights were left behind. The golden dagger is only plating over soft metal; it's worth 12 gp, and it's useless as a weapon. Other semiprecious stones and filigree that can be collected from the throne have a total value of 8 gp. </P>

<P>Cassyt will inform Doomguide Glandon if she sees any of the adventurers take any of the treasure from Sedrair's Tomb. </P>

<P>Dues for the Dead </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>11. Talking Dead </H3>

<P>Niches near the floor are filled with stacked bones, and skulls are neatly arranged about six inches apart along a ledge. The wall above the skulls bears an inscription, partially obscured by centuries of accumulated dust and cobwebs. </P>

<P>The inscription can be read if the debris is cleared away. It states, in archaic Common, &quot;A question speak you, and answer will these departed.&quot;  </P>

<P>The dead in this section of the catacombs were interred at a time when people considered it desirable to be able to speak at will with their deceased ancestors per an enchantment resembling speak with dead. </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>As with that spell, they know nothing about events that transpired after their deaths, so the skulls can't answer questions about what's been happening in the catacombs recently. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>They may recall lore about the catacombs that they knew in life, however, and some of that could include things even the faithful of Kelemvor don't know. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>More than one skull responds to most questions, and sometimes their answers are contradictory, just as any group of people's would be. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>The spell that compels these spirits to talk is ancient and fading, and the spirits themselves are only weakly held to this place. They cease responding to the characters' inquiries after they’ve answered five questions. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>12. Crime Scenes </H3>

<P>Just as important political, social, and religious figures from Phlan's history are immortalized in areas 3 and 4, some of its worst criminals are immortalized here. In this case, however, the roles of murderer and victim have been reversed. </P>

<P>This area has displays similar to those previously in the catacombs, but with one major difference. Where the previous displays were pleasant depictions of daily life, these are nightmares come to life. In one crypt, the skeletons of three, very young children are posed as if they are strangling a grown man, while another portrays five people holding a skeletal man in a chair and &quot;pouring&quot; something from a greasy, brown vial down his throat. </P>

<P>Piles of dirt and rubble have been deposited around the room. </P>

<P>The &quot;victims&quot; in these vignettes committed mass murder or other atrocious crimes, and their &quot;killers&quot; were their victims in life. Here, the victims were allowed their eternal revenge. This practice fell out of fashion long ago in Phlan, so no new burials have been added here in over a century. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>13. The Necropolis and Beyond </H3>

<P>This section of the catacombs is where most new interments take place. As such, Cassyt and other faithful of Kelemvor are more familiar with it than with other areas. </P>

<P>A thousand untold secrets exist in this place. It stretches for hundreds of feet beneath the surface; a person could explore its depths for days and not see all that it contains. </P>

<P>Rumor has it that the hidden tomb of Miltiades, a legendary undead paladin is within this section of the catacombs, though no one has claimed to have found it. </P>

<P>It's as if you've entered a subterranean city. The crypts here are modeled after surface homes and other buildings, although they're only about two-thirds the size of their real counterparts. </P>

<P>Coming from somewhere to your left, you hear sounds of scratching and scraping. How far off it's coming from is very difficult to judge in these tunnels. </P>

<P>As it is now, however, the Necropolis is infested with undead. For each hour that the adventurers spend wandering the area, roll 1d4 and consult the Wandering Monsters table to determine what the party meets. </P>

<P>If the adventurers spend enough time down here to come across all three encounters, they do not encounter any others. Additionally, Doomguide Yovir does not ask for their assistance in clearing the rest of the catacombs. </P>

<Sect>
<H5>Wandering Monsters </H5>

<Table>
<TR>
<TD>D4 Roll </TD>

<TD>Result </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>1 </TD>

<TD>Ghouls (1d4) </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>2 </TD>

<TD>Zombies (1d6) </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>3 </TD>

<TD>Skeletons (1d6) </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>4 </TD>

<TD>Nothing </TD>
</TR>
</Table>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>14A. The Sentry </H3>

<P>The Red Wizard Rorreth Monforoth and his Cult of the Dragon accomplices have taken this portion of the catacombs as their temporary base of operations. He has a modest contingent of undead gathered here. </P>

<P>A group of four zombies stand guard just inside of the </P>

<P>Dues for the Dead </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>portion of this area labeled “b”. In addition, a kobold sentinel is here, sitting in a chair, sound asleep. If the adventurers sprung any of the traps in Area 12, the zombies will not be here; having previously investigated the noise and encountered the party. The kobold, however, was sleeping too soundly to have been awoken by the racket and is still here napping. </P>

<P>This room is littered with rubble and freshly turned earth. Sitting next to a barrel next to an opening on the far side of the wall, is a kobold dozing quietly in a small wooden chair. </P>

<P>A sneaky adventurer can attack him while he is still asleep, provided that they are not seen by the zombies. Because he is unconscious, he loses his Dexterity modifier to AC and attacks are made against him with advantage, but the barrels grants him three-quarters cover, which raises his AC to 15. The first missed attack wakes the kobold who immediately starts shouting, initiating combat. </P>

<P>Upon seeing the adventurers, the kobold wants nothing more than to run into area 14b to warn the cultist fanatic and Rorreth. If the kobold is alive when his turn arrives, read: </P>

<P>The kobold grabs his sword and runs through the opening yipping excitedly. </P>

<P>Beyond the opening, you can hear raised voices and the telltale sound of swords being drawn from scabbards. </P>

<P>If the kobold is slain without having the chance to raise the alarm, the zombies attack as normal. If the kobold raises the alarm, the Thayans and cultists in area 14b begin preparing immediately. Otherwise, they are alarmed by the sounds of the adventurers combating the zombies and begin their preparation on the following round. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H4>Tactics </H4>

<P>The kobold's only job is to make as much noise as possible when it sees someone that shouldn't be there. </P>

<P>As usual, the zombies simply mob the adventurers. </P>

<Sect>
<H5>Adjusting the Encounter </H5>

<P>Here are recommendations for adjusting this combat </P>

<P>encounter. These are not cumulative. </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Very weak or weak party: remove two zombies </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Strong party: add two zombies </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Very strong party: add a ghoul </LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>14B. The Red Wizard </H3>

<P>Even at first glance, it is obvious that people have been living in this room for a long while. There are a number of straw pallets and even a pair of beds. </P>

<P>Across the room, a man in embroidered red robes with a shaved and tattooed head is hurriedly stuffing items into a haversack. As he sees you, he spits out a curse and shouts for his minions to attack. </P>

<P>The fight with the zombies in area 14a has given Rorreth the time to prepare his escape via a teleportation circle. Rorreth is accompanied by a Thayan knight (T) and a cultist (C), along with a zombie (Z), and two kobolds (K) (including the kobold from area 14a that ran here to warn them). If the adventurers spend 4 rounds or more fighting the zombies in area 14a, the Thayan knight or the cultist is invisible when the adventurers arrive (see Rorreth's Flight, below). </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Rorreth's Flight </H4>

<P>Each round that the adventurers spend fighting the zombies in area 14a, is a round that Rorreth has to pack away incriminating documents and maps. The results of his efforts are based primarily on the amount of warning he has to prepare. Beginning with the round that the kobold shouts his alarm or combat with the zombies begins (whichever occurs first), Rorreth's performs specific actions each round until they arrive and enter initiative with the inhabitants of Area 14b: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Round 1. Rorreth issues brief instructions to his guard, moves to his desk, grabs his haversack, and casts mage armor on himself. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Round 2. Rorreth packs his personal journal in his haversack and begins to sort through the remaining documents on the desk. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Round 3. He retrieves his orders from Rath Modar and secures them in his haversack. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Round 4. He casts invisibility on the Thayan knight or the cultist. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Round 5+. Rorreth continues to rummage through the desk to ensure that no incriminating evidence remains. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H4>Foes &amp; Tactics </H4>

<P>At the beginning of combat, Rorreth is 20 feet away from teleportation circle set into the floor. On his turn, he moves to the circle and teleports away as a bonus action. He has no interest in fighting the adventurers—he has </P>

<P>Dues for the Dead </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>important work to do. </P>

<P>Rorreth is an accomplished mage and unless the adventurers are able to kill or incapacitate him or prevent him from speaking, he escapes. Even if physically restrained, he uses misty step to reach to the circle and teleport away. On his turn after the adventurers arrive in Area 14b, read: </P>

<P>The wizard steps into a circle of silver runes on the floor and after muttering a single word, is enveloped in a blinding flash of green light. When your eyes clear, the man is nowhere to be seen. </P>

<P>The zombie and the Thayan knight engage the adventurers in melee while the kobolds use ranged attacks. The cultist engages the characters in melee. </P>

<P>The Thayan knight carries a vial of poison. If she begins a turn at 5 hit points or less, consumes it; killing her instantly. </P>

<P>The kobolds each have a stinkpot available to use with their sling. These deal no damage, but any creature struck by one must succeed on a DC 10 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned for 1 minute. The creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect early on a success. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H4>Cassyt </H4>

<P>Until this point, she has mostly been assisting the party as a guide and casting an occasional cantrip. However, upon seeing the wizard who is responsible for creating the undead, she becomes furious. </P>

<P>In the first round of combat, she casts bless on the three characters that she feels have performed the best in the adventure so far. If there are any undead present in the encounter, Cassyt has a single use of Turn Undead in addition to her spells. She uses it in the second round of combat. In subsequent rounds, she casts sacred flame; saving her two remaining 1st-level spell slots to cast sanctuary as needed. She prefers to attack the wizard if he is present, and the undead if he is not. </P>

<P>&quot;No longer will you profane this place with your presence!&quot; --Cassyt </P>

<Sect>
<H5>Turn Undead </H5>

<P>As an action, Cassyt presents her holy symbol and speaks a </P>

<P>prayer censuring the undead. Each undead that can see or hear </P>

<P>her within 30 feet of her must make a Wisdom saving throw. If </P>

<P>the creature fails its saving throw, it is turned for 1 minute or </P>

<P>until it takes any damage. </P>

<P>A turned creature must spend its turns trying to move as far </P>

<P>away from her as it can, and it can't willingly move to a space </P>

<P>within 30 feet of her. It also can't take reactions. For its action, </P>

<P>it can use only the Dash action or try to escape from an effect </P>

<P>that prevents it from moving. If there's nowhere to move, the </P>

<P>creature can use the Dodge action. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H4>Developments </H4>

<P>If characters are triumphant and explore the inner chambers of area 14a, they find a modest-sized room, appointed in the furnishings of living quarters—a few straw pallets, a couple chests (full of mundane personal belongings), and a table with a few chairs—all in complete disarray. Furniture has been turned over and upset, papers are strewn all about the room. Among them, only a set of maps of the catacombs are of any interest. The maps are labeled in Draconic. If the adventurers are unable to translate them, Doomguide Glandon offers to do so, even going so far as to say that they are the most accurate set of maps of the catacombs that he has ever seen and asks to keep them. </P>

<P>Area 14a also has a narrow tunnel that exits this area toward the southeast. It proceeds for about 60 feet before it appears ends in a wall of stone and rubble. This tunnel appears on the maps found by the adventurers, labeled (in Draconic) with an arrow pointing further east and a single word—“Pool.” </P>

<P>If the cultist is captured alive, he does not willingly divulge any of their secrets. Any punishment that the Cult might mete out for his betrayal would be far worse than anything the adventurers are likely willing to do. Any question to that effect is met with an insult, a mouthful of spittle, or—more likely—both. If compelled to speak, by use of charm person or similar ability, he knows only that he was sent to Valhingen to assist Rorreth in creating an army of undead. Once done, they were to use the undead to dig towards Phlan and begin the search for the Pool of Radiance. </P>

<P>While the adventurers were occupied in Area 14b, Monforoth was busy packing his haversack with any items that he felt might implicate the Red Wizards of Thay. If he escapes, he takes his haversack with him. In the unlikely event that he is killed or captured before teleporting away, however, his pack contains a journal containing rather shocking information about the Thayan wizards's plans to assist the Cult of the Dragon </P>

<P>Dues for the Dead </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>in freeing Tiamat from her imprisonment and his reluctance in joining the cause of the exile Rath Modar. </P>

<P>Additionally, there are a set of documents from Rath Modar that charge Rorreth with creating a host of undead in the catacombs beneath Valhingen Cemetery and to use them to dig their way south and east beneath Phlan in an attempt to locate the Pool of Radiance. There are extensive maps and calculations done that estimate the general direction, depth and distance that he must dig to end up beneath Valjevo Keep (where the Pool is last believed to be). </P>

<P>At this point, however, the adventurers have identified the source of the undead. With a little more work, and some assistance from the adventurers, the Kelemvorites are able to destroy the undead that remain. </P>

<Sect>
<H5>Adjusting the Encounter </H5>

<P>Here are recommendations for adjusting this combat </P>

<P>encounter. These are not cumulative. </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Very weak party: remove the Thayan knight and the zombie </LBody>
</LI>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Weak party: remove the Thayan knight and add two </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>zombies  </LI>
</L>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Strong party: add three kobolds in the back room </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl> </Lbl>

<LBody>Very strong party: add three zombies, add three kobolds in </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>the back room </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Treasure </H4>

<P>In the back room, Rorreth kept a lockbox containing 100 gp in various types of coins. Additionally, he left behind a fine writing set in the desk worth 75 gp. The Thayan knight has a pouch with 45 gp in it and the cult fanatic has a pouch containing 25 gp. The kobolds between them have 5 gp in coins along with a few worthless pieces of junk and a dead mouse. </P>
</Sect>
</Part>

<Part>
<H2>Conclusion </H2>

<P>With the adventurers successful in discovering the source of the undead within the catacombs, their work is done. While Doomguide Glandon insinuates that their assistance would be helpful in clearing out the Necropolis of undead. </P>

<P>He is dismayed at the mention of a wizard in the catacombs, and even more so at the map's mention of a &quot;pool&quot;. He goes so far to reveal that the arrow likely points in the direction of Valjevo Keep, but stops before guessing as to what the caption actually refers to. </P>

<P>Their task done, he thanks the adventurers for their work and begs the character's leave--saying he has much to discuss with his fellow clergy, the Lord Regent, and the Lord Sage. </P>

<P>Cassyt is Still Alive. Doomguide Glandon is also especially pleased with Cassyt's recounting of the events that transpired. As recognition of her efforts in the defeat of the Red Wizard, Doomguide Glandon inducts Cassyt into the Most Solemn Order of the Silent Shroud; the formal clergy of Kelemvor. </P>
</Part>

<Part>
<Sect>
<H2>Rewards </H2>

<P>Make sure note their rewards on their adventure logsheets. Give your name and DCI number (if applicable) so players can record who ran the session. </P>

<Sect>
<H3>Experience </H3>

<P>Total up all combat experience earned for defeated foes, and divide by the number of characters present in the combat. For non-combat experience, the rewards are listed per character. Give all characters in the party non-combat experience awards unless otherwise noted. </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TH>Combat Awards </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Name of Foe </TH>

<TD>XP per Foe </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Knight </TH>

<TD>700 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Rorreth (Red Wizard) </TH>

<TD>450 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Ghoul</TH>

<TD> 200 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Spy </TH>

<TD>200 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Thug</TH>

<TD> 100 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Skeleton</TH>

<TD>   50 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Zombie</TH>

<TD>   50 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Bandit</TH>

<TD>   25 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Cultist</TH>

<TD>   25 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Kobold</TH>

<TD>   25 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Non-Combat Awards </TH>

<TD/>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Task or Accomplishment </TH>

<TD>XP per Character </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Successfully disable the throne trap </TH>

<TD>75 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Convinced Cassyt not to tell </TH>

<TD>50 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Helped the Welcomers escape </TH>

<TD>50 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Welcomers left their loot behind </TH>

<TD>50 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Avoiding the Bone Pit </TH>

<TD>25 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Safely navigated stairs </TH>

<TD>25 </TD>
</TR>
</Table>

<P>The minimum total award for each character participating in this adventure is 450 experience points. The maximum total award for each character participating in this adventure is 600 experience points. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Treasure </H3>

<P>The characters receive the following treasure, divided up amongst the party. Characters should attempt to divide treasure evenly whenever possible. Gold piece </P>

<P>Dues for the Dead </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>values listed for sellable gear are calculated at their selling price, not their purchase price. </P>

<P>Consumable magic items should be divided up however the group sees fit. If more than one character is interested in a specific consumable magic item, the DM can determine who gets it randomly should the group be unable to decide. </P>

<P> Permanent magic items are divided according to a system. See the sidebar if the adventure awards </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TH>permanent magic items. </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Treasure Awards </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Item Name</TH>

<TD>  GP Value </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Payment from Doomguide Glandon </TH>

<TD>100 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Jewelry from area 3 </TH>

<TD>40 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Clothing from area 3 </TH>

<TD>60 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Trinkets from crematoria </TH>

<TD>130 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Welcomer pouches</TH>

<TD> 20 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Sedrair's crown </TH>

<TD>250 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Sedrair's crown (ruined) </TH>

<TD>50 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Sedrair's weights and balance </TH>

<TD>80 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Sedrair's gold dagger </TH>

<TD>12 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Stones from Sedrair's throne </TH>

<TD>8 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Rorreth's lockbox</TH>

<TD> 100 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Writing set</TH>

<TD> 75 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Thayan's pouch</TH>

<TD> 45 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Cultist's pouch</TH>

<TD> 25 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Kobolds' pouches </TH>

<TD>5 </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Goggles of Night </TH>

<TD/>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Wondrous item, uncommon </TH>

<TD/>
</TR>
</Table>

<P>These brass-framed goggles feel cool to the touch when worn. While wearing them, you have darkvision out to a range of 60 feet. If you already have darkvision, these goggles extend that range by 60 feet. A full description of this item can be found in the basic rules or the Dungeon Master’s Guide. </P>

<Sect>
<H5>Permanent Magic Item Distribution </H5>

<P>D&amp;D Adventurers League has a system in place to determine </P>

<P>who is awarded permanent magic items at the end of a session. </P>

<P>Each character’s logsheet contains a column to record </P>

<P>permanent magic items for ease of reference. </P>

<P> If all the players at the table agree on one character taking </P>

<P>possession of a permanent magic item, that character gets </P>

<P>the item. </P>

<P> In the event that one or more characters indicate an </P>

<P>interest in possessing a permanent magic item, the </P>

<P>character that possesses the fewest permanent magic </P>

<P>items gets the item. If there is a tie in the total number of </P>

<P>permanent magic items owned by contesting characters, </P>

<P>the item’s owner is determined randomly by the DM. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Renown </H3>

<P>All faction members earn one renown point for participating in this adventure. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Downtime </H3>

<P>Each character receives ten downtime days at the conclusion of this adventure. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Favors and Enmity </H3>

<P>The characters have the opportunity to earn the following enmity during the course of play. </P>

<P>Enmity of Doomguide Yovir Glandon. Despite his requests, you were caught stealing from the resting dead or allowed others to do so. Because of this, all members of Kelemvor's clergy in Phlan are highly distrustful of you. So long as you have this enmity, all future Charisma (Deception, Intimidation, or Persuasion) checks made against members of Kelemvor's faithful in Phlan are made with disadvantage. Additionally, the cost for any spellcasting services provided by the clergy is increased by 10%. </P>

<P>Enmity of the Welcomers. You slew one or more members of the Welcomers for little more than petty theft. So long as you have this enmity, all future Charisma (Deception, Intimidation, or Persuasion) checks made against members of the Welcomers faithful are made with disadvantage. </P>

<P>Favor of the Welcomers. You helped a small group of Welcomers escape from the Catacombs without informing Doomguide Glandon. So long as you have this favor, all future Charisma (Deception, Intimidation, or Persuasion) checks made against members of the Welcomers faithful are made with advantage. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>DM Rewards </H3>

<P>You receive 200 XP and ten downtime days for running this session. </P>

<P>Dues for the Dead </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Part>

<Part>
<H2>BBandi<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_20.jpg"/>
A</Figure>
tt </H2>

<P>MMedium humanoidd (any race), any noon-lawful alignmennt </P>

<P>AArmor Class 12 (lleather armor) HHit Points 11 (2d8 + 2) SSpeed 30 ft. </P>

<Sect>
<H6>STR DEXX CON INT WIS CHA </H6>

<P>11 (+0) 12 (++1) 12 (+1) 10 (+0) 10 (+00) 10 (+0) </P>

<P>SSenses passive Peerception 10 LLanguages any onne language (usuually Common) CChallenge 1/8 (255 XP) </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_21.jpg"/>
Appenndix: MMonst </Figure>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>AActions </H4>

<P>SScimitar. Melee WWeapon Attack: +33 to hit, reach 5 fft., one target. HHit: 4 (1d6 + 1) slashing damage. </P>

<P>LLight Crossbow. RRanged Weapon AAttack: +3 to hit, range 80 ftft./320 ft., one tarrget. Hit: 5 (1d8 ++ 1) piercing dammage. </P>
</Sect>
</Part>

<Part>
<H2>CCassyt (Acolyyte) </H2>

<P>MMedium humanoidd (human), neutrall good </P>

<P>AArmor Class 10 HHit Points 9 (2d8) SSpeed 30 ft. </P>

<Sect>
<H6>STR DEXX CON INT WIS CHA </H6>

<P>10 (+0) 10 (++0) 10 (+0) 10 (+0) 14 (+22) 11 (+0) </P>

<P>SSkills Medicine +44, Religion +2 SSenses passive Peerception 10 LLanguages any onne language (usuually Common) CChallenge 1/4 (500 XP) </P>

<P>SSpellcasting. Casssyt is a 1st-level sspellcaster. Her sspellcasting aability is Wisdom (spell save DC 112, +4 to hit with spell aattacks). Cassyt hhas the following cleric spells preppared: </P>

<P>CCantrips (at will): light, sacred flamme, thaumaturgy 1st level (3 slots): bless, cure wounnds, sanctuary </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>AActions </H4>

<P>CClub. Melee Weappon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., oone target. HHit: 2 (1d4) bludggeoning damage. </P>
</Sect>
</Part>

<Part>
<Sect>
<H2>CCultistt </H2>

<P>MMedium humanoidd (any race), any noon-good alignmentt </P>

<P>AArmor Class 12 (lleather armor) HHit Points 9 (2d8) SSpeed 30 ft. </P>
</Sect>

<P>Not for resale. Peermission granted to print or photo </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_22.jpg"/>
ter/NP STRPC Sta DEX C atisti CON INT ics WIS </Figure>

<Sect>
<H6>CCHA</H6>

<P> 11 (+0)) 12 (+1) 100 (+0) 10 (+0)) 11 (+0) 100 (+0) </P>

<P>Skills Deeception +2, Religion +2 Senses ppassive Perceptioon 10 Languagges any one language (usually Coommon) Challengge 1/8 (25 XP) </P>

<P>Dark Deevotion. The cultiist has advantagee on saving throwws against being charmed oor frightened. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Actioons </H4>

<P>Scimitarr. Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creaturee. Hit: 4 (1d6 + 1)) slashing damagge. </P>
</Sect>
</Part>

<Part>
<H2>Ghooul </H2>

<P>Medium undead, chaotic evvil </P>

<P>Armor CClass 12 Hit Poinnts 22 (5d8) Speed 300 ft. </P>

<Sect>
<H6>STR DEX CCON INT WIS CCHA</H6>

<P> 13 (+1)) 15 (+2) 100 (+0) 7 (−2) 10 (+0) 6 (−2) </P>

<P>Damagee Immunities poiison Conditioon Immunities chharmed, exhaustion, poisoned Senses ddarkvision 60 ft., passive Percepttion 10 Languagges Common Challengge 1 (200 XP) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Actioons </H4>

<P>Bite. Meelee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reacch 5 ft., one creature. Hit: 9 (22d6 + 2) piercing damage. </P>

<P>Claws. MMelee Weapon Atttack: +4 to hit, reeach 5 ft., one tarrget. Hit: 7 (22d4 + 2) slashingg damage. If the ttarget is a creature other than an elf or undeead, it must succceed on a DC 10 Constituution saving throow or be paralyzeed for 1 minute. TThe target caan repeat the savving throw at the end of each of itts turns, ennding the effect oon itself on a succcess. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Duees for the DDead </H4>
</Sect>
</Part>

<Part>
<H2>Knight </H2>

<P>Medium humanoid (any race), any alignment </P>

<P>Armor Class 18 (plate) Hit Points 52 (8d8 + 16) Speed 30 ft. </P>

<Sect>
<H6>STR DEX CON INT WIS CHA </H6>

<P>16 (+3) 11 (+0) 14 (+2) 11 (+0) 11 (+0) 15 (+2) </P>

<P>Saving Throws Con +4, Wis +2 Senses passive Perception 10 Languages any one language (usually Common) Challenge 3 (700 XP) </P>

<P>Brave. The knight has advantage on saving throws against being frightened. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Actions </H4>

<P>Multiattack. The knight makes two melee attacks. </P>

<P>Greatsword. Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 10 (2d6 + 3) slashing damage. </P>

<P>Heavy Crossbow. Ranged Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, range 100/400 ft., one target. Hit: 5 (1d10) piercing damage. </P>

<P>Leadership (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest). For 1 minute, the knight can utter a special command or warning whenever a nonhostile creature that it can see within 30 feet of it makes an attack roll or a saving throw. The creature can add a d4 to its roll provided it can hear and understand the knight. A creature can benefit from only one Leadership die at a time. This effect ends if the knight is incapacitated. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Reactions </H4>

<P>Parry. The knight adds 2 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, the knight must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon. </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TH>Kobold </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Small humanoid (kobold), lawful evil </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Armor Class 12 Hit Points 5 (2d6 − 2) Speed 30 ft. </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>STR 7 (−2) </TH>

<TD>DEX 15 (+2) </TD>

<TD>CON 9 (−1) </TD>

<TD>INT 8 (−1) </TD>

<TD>WIS 7 (−2) </TD>

<TD>CHA 8 (−1) </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Senses darkvision 60 ft., passive Perception 8 Languages Common, Draconic Challenge 1/8 (25 XP) </TH>

<TD/>
</TR>
</Table>

<P>Sunlight Sensitivity. While in sunlight, the kobold has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight. </P>

<P>Pack Tactics. The kobold has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the kobold’s allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn’t incapacitated. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Actions </H4>

<P>Dagger. Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage. </P>

<P>Sling. Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. Hit: 4 (1d4 + 2) bludgeoning damage. </P>
</Sect>
</Part>

<Part>
<Sect>
<H2>Rorreth (Red Wizard) </H2>

<Table>
<TR>
<TH>Medium humanoid (human), neutral evil </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Armor Class 12 (15 with mage armor) Hit Points 22 (5d8) Speed 30 ft. </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>STR 9 (−1) </TH>

<TD>DEX 14 (+2) </TD>

<TD>CON 11 (+0) </TD>

<TD>INT 17 (+3) </TD>

<TD>WIS 12 (+1) </TD>

<TD>CHA 11 (+0) </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Saving Throws Int +5, Wis +3 Skills Arcana +5, History +5 Senses passive Perception 11 Languages Common, Draconic, Dwarvish, Elvish Challenge 2 (450 XP) </TH>

<TD/>
</TR>
</Table>

<P>Spellcasting. The red wizard is a 4th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). The mage has the following wizard spells prepared: </P>

<P>Cantrips (at will): light, fireblast, shocking grasp 1st level (4 slots): shield, mage armor, magic missile 2nd level (3 slots): invisibility, misty step </P>

<Sect>
<H4>Actions </H4>

<P>Quarterstaff. Melee Weapon Attack: +1 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 3 (1d8 – 1) bludgeoning damage. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Dues for the Dead </H4>

<P>Not for resale. Permission granted to print or photocopy this document for personal use only. </P>

<Sect>
<P>Spy </P>

<P>Medium humanoid (any race), any alignment </P>

<P>Armor Class 12 Hit Points 27 (6d8) Speed 30 ft. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H6>STR DEX CON INT WIS CHA </H6>

<P>10 (+0) 15 (+2) 10 (+0) 12 (+1) 14 (+2) 16 (+3) </P>

<P>Skills Deception +5, Insight +4, Investigation +5, Perception +6, </P>

<P>Persuasion +5, Sleight of Hand +4, Stealth +4 Senses passive Perception 16 Languages any two languages Challenge 1 (200 XP) </P>

<P>Cunning Action. On each of its turns, the spy can use a bonus action to take the Dash, Disengage, or Hide action. </P>
</Sect>

<P>Sneak Attack (1/Turn). The spy deals an extra 7 (2d6) damage when it hits a target with a weapon attack and has advantage on the attack roll, or when the target is within 5 feet of an ally of the spy that isn’t incapacitated and the spy doesn’t have disadvantage on the attack roll. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H4>Actions </H4>

<P>Multiattack. The spy makes two melee attacks. </P>

<P>Shortsword. Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage. </P>

<P>Hand Crossbow. Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. Hit: 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage. </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TH>Skeleton </TH>

<TH/>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Medium undead, lawful evil </TH>

<TD/>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Armor Class 13 (armor scraps) Hit Points 13 (2d8 + 4) Speed 30 ft. </TH>

<TD/>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>STR10 (+0) </TH>

<TD>DEX 14 (+2) </TD>

<TD>CON 15 (+2) </TD>

<TD>INT 6 (−2) </TD>

<TD>WIS 8 (−1) </TD>

<TD>CHA 5 (−3) </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Damage Vulnerabilities bludgeoning Damage Immunities poison </TH>

<TD/>

<TD/>

<TD/>
</TR>
</Table>

<P>Condition Immunities exhaustion, poisoned Senses darkvision 60 ft., passive Perception 9 Languages understands all languages it knew in life but can’t </P>

<P>speak Challenge 1/4 (50 XP) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Actions </H4>

<P>Shortsword. Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage. </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>
</Part>

<Part>
<H2>Thug </H2>

<P>Medium humanoid (any race), any non-good alignment </P>

<P>Armor Class 11 (leather armor) Hit Points 32 (5d8 + 10) Speed 30 ft. </P>

<Sect>
<H6>STR DEX CON INT WIS CHA </H6>

<P>15 (+2) 11 (+0) 14 (+2) 10 (+0) 10 (+0) 11 (+0) </P>

<P>Skills Intimidation +2 Senses passive Perception 10 Languages any one language (usually Common) Challenge 1/2 (100 XP) </P>

<P>Pack Tactics. The thug has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the thug’s allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn’t incapacitated. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Actions </H4>

<P>Multiattack. The thug makes two melee attacks. </P>

<P>Mace. Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. Hit: 5 (1d6 + 2) bludgeoning damage. </P>

<P>Heavy Crossbow. Ranged Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, range 100/400 ft., one target. Hit: 5 (1d10) piercing damage. </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TH>Zombie </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Medium undead, neutral evil </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Armor Class 8 Hit Points 22 (3d8 + 9) Speed 20 ft. </TH>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>STR13 (+1) </TH>

<TD>DEX 6 (−2) </TD>

<TD>CON 16 (+3) </TD>

<TD>INT 3 (−4) </TD>

<TD>WIS 6 (−2) </TD>

<TD>CHA 5 (−3) </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TH>Saving Throws Wis +0 Damage Immunities poison Condition Immunities poisoned </TH>

<TD/>

<TD/>

<TD/>
</TR>
</Table>

<P>Senses darkvision 60 ft., passive Perception 8 Languages understands the languages it knew in life but can’t </P>

<P>speak Challenge 1/4 (50 XP) </P>

<P>Undead Fortitude. If damage reduces the zombie to 0 hit points, it must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5 </P>

<P>+ the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, the zombie drops to 1 hit point instead. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Actions </H4>

<P>Slam. Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 4 (1d6 + 1) bludgeoning damage. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Dues for the Dead </H4>

<P>Not for resale. Permission granted to print or photocopy this document for personal use only. </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_23.jpg"/>
Appendix: Map oof thee Cataacombbs </Figure>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Duees for the DDead </H4>
<Figure>

<ImageData src="images/DDEX14_DuesfortheDead_img_24.jpg"/>
Appendixx: Maap of tthe Reed Wizzard’s Lair </Figure>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H4>Duees for the DDead </H4>

<P>Not for resale. Peermission granted to print or photocopy this document for personal usse only. 25 </P>
</Sect>
</Part>
</TaggedPDF-doc>
